

Soohwan Kim

TUNIB CO-FOUNDER · AL ENGINEER

4F, 20 Pangyo-ro 289beon-gil, Seongnam District, Republic of Korea

□ (+82) 10-4564-4668 | **S**sh951011@gmail.com | **S**sooftware.io | **S**sooftware | **S**soo-hwan

"AI / Startup / Open-source / Competition"

Summary_

I am an A.I. research engineer with several years of experience in the fields of speech and natural language processing. Prior to this, I worked at Kakao Brain. Currently, I am one of the co-founders of a tech startup called TUNiB, alongside my former teammates from Kakao Brain.

Our goal is to develop advanced A.I. technology, striving to create chatbots with conversational abilities akin to Samantha from the movie "Her." While our current chatbot service, Dearmate, may not yet reach Samantha's level of conversation, we believe that in the near future, we will be able to achieve such a milestone.

Professional Experience

TUNIB

Co-FOUNDER/ALLEAD

Mar. 2021 - Present

Co-founded with former Kakao Brain team members.

- Raised approximately 3 billion won in seed investment from Pearl Abyss Capital, DSC Investment, and Naver D2. (2021.10)
- Ruisea approximatery's billion worm seed investment from Federal Abys's Capital, DSC investment, and navel D2.
- [NLP] Lead development the Dearmate project: <u>https://https://demo.dearmate.ai</u>
- [NLP] Development of own sLLM named Cheetah
- [NLP] Responsible for modeling Blenderbot dataset projects (national project)
- [NLP] Responsible for modeling KommonGen dataset projects (national project)
- [NLP] Development of the TUNiB demo NLP technology: https://tunibridge.ai
- [NLP] Lead the Safety Check project: https://tunibridge.ai/safety
- [NLP] Developing an open-domain dialogue system.
- [NLP] Development of the framework for few-shot evaluation of autoregressive language models.
- [NLP] Led the text data collection (1.2TB) (used in the Polyglot project)
- [NLP] TUNiB-ELECTRA: https://github.com/tunib-ai/tunib-electra
- [NLP] NLP-Tasks: natural language processing tasks and examples
- [NLP] Implementation of Luna-Transformer: Linear Unified Nested Attention
- [Competition] 3rd place in 2022 National AI Grand Challenge NLP (2 billion won in subsidies for commercialization)
- [Competition] 1st place in 2022 National AI Online Competition NLP (200 million won in subsidies for commercialization)
- [Competition] 3rd place in 2021 National Al Grand Challenge Speech Understanding
- [Competition] 1st place in 2021 National Al Online Competition NLP (300 million won in subsidies for commercialization)

Kakao Brain Pangyo, Gyunggi

Al Engineer (Full-time)

Nov. 2020 - Feb. 2021

- · Team Leader: Kyubyong Park
- Speech and natural language processing team.
- [NLP] PORORO: Platform Of neuRal mOdels for natuRal language prOcessing: https://github.com/kakaobrain/pororo
- [SPEECH] Implementation of Conformer: Convolution-augmented Transformer for Speech Recognition
- [SPEECH] Implementation of Speech Transformer
- [SPEECH] Implementation of the "Listen, Attend and Spell" model based on the Fairseg framework.

Internship

Kakao BrainMapo, Seoul

AI ENGINEER Aug. 2020 - Oct. 2020

- Team Leader: Kyubyong Park
- Speech and natural language processing team.
- [SPEECH] Multilingual Text-To-Speech
- [SPEECH] English, Chinese, and Korean Speech Recognition using Wav2vec 2
- [SPEECH] Korean Wav2vec 2 pre-training

Spoken Language Lab (Sogang Univ.)

Mapo, Seoul

Mar. 2020 - Aug. 2020

Undergraduate Researcher

• Department of Computer Science & Engineering Sogang University

- Advisor: Prof. Ji-Hwan Kim
- Homepage: https://speech.sogang.ac.kr

JULY 29, 2023 SOOHWAN KIM · RÉSUMÉ 1



Dearmate

ALLEAD 2022 - Present

- Al chatbot platform with a variety of characters with unique personas.
- Running the service with our own sLLM(named Cheetah).
- · Quickly adding new characters and improving dialogue performance.
- [Web Demo] [Play Store] [App Store]

TUNiBridge 2021 - Present

ALLEAD

- NLP Cloud API Services
- API Services: Text Safety Check, Emotion Prediction, Dialect Translation etc.
- Portfolio: NIA, wrtn, Nexon, Krafton, UpStage, Mirae Asset etc.
- Link: https://tunibridge.ai

OpenSource Project

Pororo

KAKAO BRAIN Aug 2020 - Feb 2021

- · Library that can solve more than 30 natural language processing tasks in just 3-4 lines with pre-trained models.
- Developed speech related modules. (Automatic Speech Recognition, Text To Speech)
- Link: https://github.com/kakaobrain/pororo

OpenSpeech / KoSpeech

PERSONAL Jan 2020 - Jun 2021

- · Framework that enables easy creation of speech recognition models of various models and various languages.
- Dozens of models including Transformers, Conformer, Transformers, and Listen Attend Spell.
- Link(OpenSpeech): https://github.com/openspeech-team/openspeech
- Link(KoSpeech): https://github.com/sooftware/kospeech

TUNIB Electra

TUNIB Aug 2021 - Sep 2021

- Released two version of ELECTRA models. (Korean-English bilingual model, Korean-only model).
- · Conducted performance comparison experiments between several tokenizers made using the Tokenizers library.
- · Link: https://github.com/tunib-ai/tunib-electra

Conformer

PERSONAL Jan 2021 - Jan 2021

- PyTorch implementation of "Conformer: Convolution-augmented Transformer for Speech Recognition" (INTERSPEECH 2020)
- · Link: https://github.com/sooftware/conformer

Education

Kwangwoon University

BACHELOR OF ENGINEERING IN ELECTRONICS AND COMMUNICATION

• Major: Electronics & Communication Engineering, Minor: Data Science

- Major GPA: 3.90 / 4.5, Total GPA: 3.67 / 4.5
- · Relevant Coursework
 - Machine Learning Database
 - AI & Speech Processing Digital Signal Processing
- Data Structures Data Mining
- · Operating System
- Computer Architecture
- System Programming
- · Computer Network
- · Data Communication

Mar. 2014 - Feb. 2021

· Network Programming

Awards

- 2020.11 President's Award, Multi-Y Capstone Design Competition
- 2020.11 **People's Choice Award**, Multi-Y Capstone Design Competition
- 2019.10 People's Choice Award, Software start-up idea contest Fall
- 2019.04 People's Choice Award, Software start-up idea contest Spring
- 2018.08 Outstanding Award, Samsung Multi-Campus
- Honors
 - 2020.03 Honors Scholarship, Samsong Scholarship
 - 2019.03 Honors Scholarship, Samsong Scholarship
 - 2019.03 Academic Scholarship, Kwangwoon University
 - 2018.09 Academic Scholarship, Kwangwoon University
 - 2018.03 Academic Scholarship, Kwangwoon University

Military Service

Republic of Korea Marine Corps

he 2nd Marine Devisior

Sep. 2015 - Jun. 2017

• Served and discharged from Republic of Korea Marine Corps as Signaller.

Talks

SERGEANT

The development process of the TUNiB Electra model

Seoul. S.Kored

2021 SSDC (SAMSUNG SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT CONFERENCE)

Nov. 2021

Aug. 2021

• Presentation Session: YouTube

Korean Speech Recognition

Seoul S Kore

• Presentation Video: YouTube

Know-how to win the 2021 AI online competition

Senul S Kored

2021 Al Online Competition, Pangyo Al Camp

Aug. 2021

• Presentation Video: YouTube

Writing.

2021 LANGCON

Technical Blog sooftware.ic

QUICK PEEK Aug. 2018 - Present

• Beam search: https://sooftware.io/beamsearch

- Attention Mechanism: https://sooftware.io/attention
- Seq2seq: https://sooftware.io/seq2seq

Skills_____

Language Python, C, Java, Shell Script, SQL

Deep Learning PyTorch, PyTorch-Lightning, Transformers, Fairseq, DeepSpeed **MLOps** Triton Inference Server, Faster Transformer, Docker, FastAPI

Publication _

[1] Chaewon Park, **Soohwan Kim**, Kyubyong Park, and Kunwoo Park, "A Korean Hate Speech Dataset with Toxicity Scales: Cognitive Reflection Test for Improving Model Fairness", pre-print, 2023.

[2] <u>Soohwan Kim</u>, Seyoung Bae, and Cheolhwang Won, "Open-Source Toolkit for End-to-End Korean Speech Recognition", ELSEVIER, SIMPAC (Software Impacts), Vol.7, 100054, 2021.

[3] Soohwan Kim, Seyoung Bae, Cheolhwang Won, and Suwon Park, "KoSpeech: Open-Source Toolkit for End-to-End Korean Speech Recognition", arXiv, 2009.03092, 2020.

Competitions _____

2022	3rd Ranked , National Al Grand Challenge - Policy-assisted Al	
2022	1st Ranked, National AI Online Competition - Machine Reading Comprehension Track	
2021	3rd Ranked, National AI Grand Challenge - Speech Understanding Track	
2021	1st Ranked, National AI Online Competition - Conversation Sentiment Classification Track	
2020	3rd Ranked, National AI Grand Challenge - Speech Understanding Track	
2019	Finalist (12th Ranked), Naver Al Hackathon - Speech	

Honors & Awards _____

2022	Minister's Award - Ministry of Science and ICT (MSIT), 2022 National AI Grand Challenge	
2022	Minister's Award - Ministry of Science and ICT (MSIT), 2022 National AI Online Competition	
2021	President's Award - IITP, 2021 National AI Grand Challenge	
2021	President's Award - NIPA, 2021 National AI Online Competition	

July 29, 2023 Soohwan Kim · Résumé